Now that we have seen a valid solution to
the critical section problem, let's look into
how hardware can help us in this context.
As mentioned in previous lectures, collaboration
between the OS and the hardware is essential
and it can be observed in many modules and
aspects of modern OSs.
The first option we look at is a function
that allows users to disable/enable interrupts
on one specific core, as shown in the slide.
Such a function could in principle help, but
you probably agree with me that disabling
interrupts can lead to limited ability of
interleaving programs.
In a sense, the user might be given "too much
power" and affect/limit the OS control.
More importantly, the problem with this solution
is that by disabling the interrupts on one
core, threads running on different cores are
still able to lead to behavior that does not
satisfy the critical section problem.
Something better is provided by Read-Modify-Write
(RMW) operations.
In this case we are not talking of individual
atomic reads or writes, but of an atomic operation
that performs both a read and a write.
Examples of these operations are TestAndSet,
FetchAndAdd, CompareAndSwap, and so on.
We will look at some of these next.
Let's try with the TestAndSet (TAS) instruction.
As shown in the slide, the function gets a
boolean variable, sets it to true and returns
the previous value.
As I said, this instruction is executed atomically,
so it either runs in its entirety or it does
not.
Under the hood, the hardware is either disabling
interrupts if the system is uniprocessor or
locking the system bus if the system is a
multiprocessor one.
Now, if you think about it, you will agree
with me that if the target variable is set
to false and N concurrent threads invoke the
TAS, then only one will get false in return.
If you agree with this, then probably you
can see how we can use the TAS in the entry
section as shown in the example.
A thread can enter its critical section only
if the TAS returns false.
If there are concurrent invocations, the TAS
will only return false to one thread, and
no other thread will be able to enter its
critical section until another thread exits
its own and sets lock to false.
Please, take a moment and try to reason formally
about whether this solution meets the mutual
exclusion, progress and fairness properties.
An alternative instruction we could use is
the CompareAndSwap (CAS).
In this case, the instructions that are run
atomically will set a given value to a given
variable only if the current value of such
variable is the expected one.
If you look at this alternative formulation
of the critical section, you will see it's
equivalent to the one using the TAS.
Something worth noticing about these solutions
is that they are busy waiting / spinning.
Each thread will keep consuming CPU cycles
until it manages to enter its critical section,
which is a waste of resources.
If you have tried to argue yourself about
whether these are valid solutions to the critical
section problem, you probably have reached
the conclusion that from the fairness perspective,
they are also not optimal.
More concretely, they can lead to starvation,
with the same thread being the one that keeps
entering its critical section and other threads
not managing to do so.
The third point to think about is the underlying
OS scheduling mechanism.
Even if in this lecture we have not really
made any assumption on the scheduling mechanism
the underlying OS is using, you should not
think we do not need to make assumptions when
looking at a specific solution.
For instance, if we assume the OS is running
a non-preemptive priority-based scheduler
and the thread that is spinning in its entry
section is the one with the highest priority,
then the solution can lead to a deadlock and
no thread is actually able to make any progess.
If we now go back to the observation about
starvation, let's look at an alternative formulation
that can help us achieve better fairness.
Let's assume the entry and exit sections are
as shown in this slide.
Besides a shared lock variable initially set
to false, we have a shared array of boolean
values called waiting.
The array has one boolean per thread, initially
set to false.
In its entry section, before entering the
while loop, each thread shares its will of
entering the critical section by setting its
entry in the waiting array to true.
The thread will stay in the loop until it
manages to run TAS (as before) and while its
waiting entry remains true.
After exiting the while loop and before entering
its critical section, the thread sets its
entry in waiting to false.
Now let's look at what happens after the thread
exits its critical section.
The thread circles over the waiting array,
starting from the next thread in the array
(as if the buffer is circular) and then stops
as soon as it finds one entry for which waiting
is true or if completes the circle.
If no other thread is waiting in its loop
inside its entry section, then this thread
sets lock to false, so some other thread that
wants to enter its critical section later
on can do so.
Notice that the thread that enters its critical
section next could be the thread that just
set lock to false, but this cannot happen
for an unbounded number of times (if another
thread is waiting), since if another thread
also wants to enter the critical section,
then its entry in waiting will be true and
the thread that manages to enter its critical
section will then hand over the lock in its
exit section, as shown in line 14.
As before, try to formally reason about whether
this solution is valid or not by yourselves.